Lights.
ライティングについて、見ていきます。
Just like the real world, in Unity
実世界のように、Unity は
we use lights to illuminate our scenes.
ライトによりシーンを照らすことが出来ます。
Without lights nothing would be visible
ライトがなければ、シーン上のカメラには
to the cameras in our scene.
何も表示されません。
Broadly there are two types of lighting in Unity
Unity には大きく分けて二種類のライティングがあり
dynamic and baked lighting.
動的ライティングおよび焼き込みされたライティングです。
Dynamic lighting is calculated in
動的ライティングはゲームが実行されているとき、
real time while our game is running.
リアルタイムで計算されます。
This can be achieved simply by adding lights to our scene.
シーンにライトを追加することで、動的ライティングは行なわれます。
Baked lighting is calculated offline
焼き込みされたライティングはオフラインで計算されたものであり、
and saved to a texture.
テクスチャに保存されています。
These lighting texture maps are then applied
このライティング テクスチャ マップは
to the baked objects in the scene
シーンに焼き込みされたオブジェクトに適用されることで
for improved performance.
パフォーマンスを改善します。
For more information on baked and dynamic
焼き込みされたライティングおよび動的ライティングの
lighting see the lesson linked below.
詳細については下にあるリンクを確認して下さい。
To light our scene we use the Light component.
シーンをライティングするにはライト コンポーネントを使用します。
Like all components in Unity
Unity の他のすべてのコンポーネントのように
the light component is attached to a game object.
ライト コンポーネントはゲームオブジェクトにアタッチされています。
We can move the light within our scene
シーンの中のライトを移動するには
using the game objects transform.
ゲームオブジェクトの位置調整ツールを使用することが出来ます。
The light component has four different types of lights.
ライト コンポーネントには 4 種類のライトがあります。
The Point Light, the Directional Light,
ポイント ライト（Point Light）、方向性ライト（Directional Light）、
the Spot Light and for baked
スポットライト（Spot Light）、および
lighting only, the Area Light.
焼き込みされたライティングのみで使用できるエリアライト（Area Light）です。
Each of these types behave completely differently
これらの種類はゲームの見映えにに関して、
in the way they effect the look of our game.
まったく異なる挙動をします。
The point light behaves like a bare light bulb.
ポイントライトは 裸電球のような挙動をします。
The point light illuminates objects in the scene
ポイントライトのライティングはシーンのオブジェクトを
based on the light's position in the scene.
シーンにおけるライトの位置にもとづいてライティングします。
Rotation has no influence on the light
回転はライティングにまったく影響せず、
as this light shines equally
これは全ての方向に均等に
in all directions.
照らすためです。
The directional light behaves like the sun.
方向性ライトは太陽のような役割を果たします。
Directional lights effect all the objects in the scene
方向性ライトはシーンにおける全てのオブジェクトに影響します。
lighting them based on the direction of the light
ゲームオブジェクトの回転によりセットされたライトの方向に
set by the game object's rotation.
もとづいてライティングします。
Position in the scene is irrelevant.
シーンにおける位置はまったく影響しません。
Spot lights behave like a flashlight
スポットライトは懐中電灯または
or headlamps on a car.
車のヘッドランプのような挙動をします。
They point in a direction based
Transform の回転にもとづいた
on their transform's rotation
方向を向いています。
and illuminate all objects within a cone.
そして、その三角錐の中のすべてのオブジェクトを照らします。
So spot lights respond to both
スポットライトは回転および位置に
rotation and position.
影響を受けます。
Area lights only work when baking a light map.
エリアライトはライトマップを焼き込みするときのみ動作します。
Area lights shine in all directions to
エリアライトは四角平面の片側の
one side of a rectangular plane.
すべての方向を照らします。
In addition to these four main types of lights
4 種類のライトに加えて
there are two other items that can
シーンのライティングに影響することができる
influence the lighting in the scene.
アイテムがふたつあります。
Ambient light and emissive materials.
これは環境ライト（Ambient Light）および自己発光（emissive）マテリアルです。
Ambient light controls global
環境ライトはシーンにおける
non directional lighting in the scene.
グローバルな方向性のないライトを制御します。
Ambient light works with both dynamic
環境ライトは動的ライティングおよび
and baked lighting.
焼き込みされたライティングで動作します。
For complete control set the
完全に制御するためには
ambient light to black
環境ライトを黒色にセットして、
and use only the lighting in the scene.
シーン上のライティングのみ使用します。
Emissive materials are created by
自己発光マテリアルは
setting the emission property in an
Emission プロパティを
appropriate self-illuminating shader.
対応する自己発光するシェーダーでセットすることにより作成します。
Emissive materials work only with baked lighting.
自己発光マテリアルは焼き込みされたライティングでのみ動作します。
For more information see the lessons link below.
より詳細については下のリンクからレッスンを参照して下さい。
There are several properties that let us
ライトをカスタマイズするためのプロパティが
customise the light.
いくつかあります。
Range determines how far a light is
Range によりライトが
emitted from the centre of the game object
ライト コンポーネントをアタッチしたゲームオブジェクトの中心から
holding the light component.
どれだけ離れて発行されているかを示します。
Range only works with point and spot lights.
Range はポイントライトおよびスポットライトでのみ動作します。
When we have spot selected as our light type
もしライトの種類として Spot を選択した場合、
we also have access to the
Spot Angle プロパティに対して
spot angle property.
アクセスすることが出来ます。
Spot angle determines the angle of the cone
Spot Angle によりスポットライトが使用する三角錐の傾斜角を
used by the spot light in degrees.
角度単位で使用できます。
Colour will control the colour of the light.
Color によりライトのカラーを制御できます。
Note the scene gizmo colour will change
シーン Gizmo の色は
to match the colour property.
Color プロパティにあわせて変化するので注意して下さい。
Intensity controls the brightness of the light
Intensity はRange とは独立して
and this is independent of range.
ライトの明るさを制御します。
When trying to light a scene, a combination
シーンをライティングするとき、
of all of these properties are needed
効果的なライティングを実現するためには
to create effective lighting.
これらのプロパティの組み合わせが必要です。
Our lights may appear brighter as we
ライトは Intensity および Range を増加させると
increase both intensity and range.
より明るく感じるかもしれません。
But they both have different behaviours
しかし、それぞれに異なった挙動をして、
in the way that they light our scene.
シーンのライティングを行います。
As well as simple illumination
シンプルに照らすライトにより
lights can also use a number of effects.
複数のエフェクトが使用できます。
Shadows, flares, halos
シャドウ、フレア、ハロー
and something called a Cookie.
および、クッキーとよばれるものです。
A cookie acts like a virtual mask
クッキーはバーチャル マスクまたは
or flag in front of the light
ライトの前のフラグの働きをして
to create a patterned shadow.
パターンのあるシャドウを作成します。
Cookies use the alpha channel of a texture
クッキーはテクスチャのアルファチャネルを使用して
to give the light a projected shadow pattern.
ライトに照らされたシャドウのパターンを提供します。
Cookies must be a 2D texture
クッキーは スポットライトおよび方向性ライトで作業をするとき、
when working with spot and directional lights.
2D テクスチャである必要があります。
Cookies must be a cube map
クッキーはポイントライト使用するとき
when using a point light.
キューブマップである必要があります。
This makes sense when you think about
これはスポットライトおよび方向性ライトが
the fact that both spot and directional lights
一つの方向に照らしていて、
are shining in one direction
ポイントライトがすべての方向に照らしていることを考えると
and point lights are shining in all directions.
納得がいきます。
When using directional lights
方向性ライトを使用するとき
there is an option to change the cookie's size,
クッキーの Size を変更するオプションがあり、
scaling the pattern in the scene.
シーンのパターンをスケールできます。
Cookies do not work with area lights.
クッキーはエリアライトとは、一緒に使用できません。
When using baked lighting cookies only work
焼き込みされたライティング クッキー は
with spot lights and are ignored
スポットライトとしか動作せず、
for baked point lights and baked directional lights.
焼き込みされたポイントライトや、焼き込みされた方向性ライトとは使用できません。
Shadows.
次は、シャドウです。
There are two types of shadows available
ライトからシャドウを投影するとき、
when casting shadows from a light.
二種類のシャドウがあります。
Hard and Soft shadows.
ハードシャドウおよびソフトシャドウです。
Hard shadows are the most efficient.
ハードシャドウはもっともパフォーマンスは軽くなります。
Soft shadows are often more convincing.
一方、ソフトシャドウのほうが見映えが良い場合が多くなります。
But they're most expensive to render.
しかしソフトシャドウはレンダリングが高価です。
When rendering shadows there are several options.
シャドウをレンダリングするとき、いくつかのオプションがあります。
Strength sets the value of the
Strngth はシャドウの暗さの値を
darkness of the shadow.
セットします。
Adjust this value until the shadow seems
シーンの中でシャドウが正しいと感じるまで
correct in the scene.
値を調整して下さい。
Full strength, or the value of 1
最大の強度にするには値は 1 ですが、
is often too strong.
しばしば強すぎます。
Resolution is simply a quality setting.
Resolution は単に画像の品質設定です。
By default a light will use the value
デフォルトでは、ライトは品質設定（Quality Settings）で使用された
you set in quality settings.
値を使用します。
These values can be overridden here
これらの値はライトごとに
on a per light basis.
上書きすることができます。
For more information see the lesson on
より多くの情報については
quality settings.
品質設定（Quality Settings）に関するレッスンを参照して下さい。
Bias controls an offset value
Bias はすべてのライトからの
to optimise shadow rendering
シャドウ レンダリングを最適化する
from any given light.
オフセット値を制御します。
Bias is a setting that effects how far
Bias はオブジェクトからどれだけ遠くシャドウが
from objects the shadows will start.
開始するかに影響する設定です。
Values that are too low will produce artefacts,
値が小さすぎる場合は画像の乱れを発生させ、
but values that are too high will mean
値が大きすぎる場合は
that the objects appear to be hovering.
オブジェクトが浮遊しているようにみえます。
When using directional lights with soft shadows
ソフトシャドウつきの方向性ライトを使用するとき
there are two additional settings.
ふたつの追加設定があります。
Softness and softness fade.
Softness および Softness Fade です。
The softness is how harsh
Softness は
the lines of the shadow will be
シャドウの線の粗さであり、
and the softness fade is a measure of
Softness Fade は
how far from the camera
カメラからどれだけ離れたところまで
the soft shadows are drawn.
ソフトシャドウが描画されるか表します。
For more information please see the
より詳細については
documentation on lights linked below.
下のリンクにあるライトのドキュメントを参照して下さい。
Draw Halo will draw the default
Draw Halo によりシーンのライトの周りの
scene halo around the light.
デフォルトのハローを描画します。
Halos respond to both the range
ハローはライトの Range および
and intensity of the light.
Instensity に影響します。
Details for the default halo can be
デフォルトのハローについての詳細は
set in the scene's render settings.
シーンのレンダリング設定でセットされます。
To override the default halo
デフォルトのハローを上書きするには
this setting should be left off
この設定はオフとすべきであり、
and an individual halo component
個別のハロー コンポーネントを
should be used instead.
代わりに使用すべきです。
A flare is similar to a halo but
フレアはハローに似ていますが、
imitates a bright light source
眼鏡を通した明るいライトの光源を
seen through optical glass.
再現しています。
When a flare asset is loaded in to the flare slot
フレア アセットが Flare スロットにロードされるとき
the light will render using a lens flare.
ライトはレンズ フレアを使用してレンダリングします。
Flares only respond to the intensity of the light.
フレアはライトの Intensity にのみ影響を受けます。
A lens flare component can be attached
レンズ フレア コンポーネントは
directly to the game object
ゲームオブジェクトに直接アタッチできます。
but then the flare property on the light
しかしライトの Flare プロパティは
should remain empty or there will be
空のままとしないと
two flares rendered on the light.
ライトには二つのフレアがレンダリングされます。
A flare layer component must be attached
フレア レイヤー コンポーネントは
to a camera for that camera
カメラにアタッチしないと
to render a flare element.
カメラはフレアをレンダリングできません。
Render Mode.
次はレンダリング モードです。
There are two different methods
動的ライトをレンダリングするには
of rendering dynamic lights
二種類の方法があり、
using vertex lighting
頂点ライティングを使用する方法と、
and using per pixel lighting.
ピクセル ライティングを使用する方法です。
Vertex lighting is usually the fastest
頂点ライティングは通常、もっとも高速であり
and calculates the scene's lighting
そしてオブジェクト メッシュの頂点で
at the vertices of an objects mesh.
シーンのライティングを計算します。
The lighting is then interpolated
ライティングはメッシュ表面上を
over the surface of the mesh.
補間します。
Per pixel lighting is calculated at every screen pixel
ピクセル ライティングは画面上のすべてのピクセルを計算し、
which is more expensive.
このほうがより高価です。
While pixel lighting is slower to render it does
ピクセル ライティングはよりレンダリングに時間がかかりますが
allow for some effects that are not possible
頂点ライティングでは実現できないエフェクトを
with vertex lighting.
可能にします。
Normal mapping, light cookies and real time
法線マッピング、ライト クッキーおよび
shadows are only rendered for pixel lights.
リアルタイム シャドウはピクセル ライトでのみレンダリングされます。
Spot light shapes and specular highlights
スポットライトの形および鏡面のハイライト
are much better when rendered
はピクセルモードでレンダリングしたとき
in pixel mode as well.
遥かに良い結果となります。
Lights have a big impact on rendering speed.
ライトはレンダリング スピードに大きな影響があります。
The number of pixel lights can be limited
ピクセル ライトの数は
in the quality settings by
ピクセル ライティングの Count プロパティを使用して
using the pixel light count property.
画質設定（Quality Settings）で上限を決めることが出来ます。
When you are in the forward rendering path
フォワード レンダリング パスにいるとき
render mode gives explicit control
レンダリング モードは
over whether a light should be rendered
ライトが頂点ライティングあるいはピクセルライトでレンダリングされるか
as a vertex or pixel light.
明示的に制御できます。
Important will force the light to be
Important にすることでライトは
rendered per pixel and not important
ピクセル ライティングが適用され、Important としないと
will force the light to be rendered
ライトのレンダリングは
in a faster mode using per vertex
より高速なモードである頂点ライティングか、
or spherical harmonics.
球面調和ライティングを使用します。
For more information on render mode and
レンダリング パスおよび
render path see the documentation link below.
レンダリングモードに関する詳細は下のリンクのドキュメントを参照して下さい。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)